Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 6 -- Letters to Franklin 1781-1782 Mss.B.F85inventory06
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Languishing for a word in reply to his last five letters; a volume of opuscula on various philosophical subjects kept back for Franklin's sanction; on receipt of Franklin's answer, will send the whole collection to M. Le Bègue de Presle to be printed. Account of two curious experiments, one the production of a certain kind of clear smoke, the other a manner of setting fire to a metal wire. His ignorance of the business enterprise be engaged in with Mr. Wharton; Dr. Bancroft and Mr. Coffyn. Trusts the Peace Conference has been sucessful; hopes his countrymen will take revenge upon the barbarous English.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Trumbull, John. Bilbao
    Offers congratulations on the capture of Cornwallis and the flattering situation of affairs in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 9; A.L.S. 1p.; de Benyowsky, Count. Paris
    Requesting Dr. Franklin to forward him the promised letters of recommendation, as he is about to start on his journey.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Edes, Caroline. Versailles
    Fearing Franklin may not know how to direct an answer to her letter of the day before, sends her address.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Gottkier, ------
    Burning with a desire to live in the United States; dedicates to Franklin the small poem adjoined.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Franks, David
    Much insulted at the treatment he has received from Mr. Hector and the Major de Place of Brest; has been twice arrested and is at present a prisoner writing with sergeant at his back; begs that the Marquis de Castries be asked to write to this Hector, who is in possession of his commission, passport, letters of credit and of recommendation, with Mr. W.T. Franklin's last letter ordering him to Brest.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 10; L.S. 2p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Asked Messrs. Van Arp and Co., Directors of the "Aurora" and "Liberty" to make some demand for the pretended damages; in reply they demanded 60,000 francs; Mr.[John] Adams's opinion; they approve of Franklin's resolution to have the matter settled by arbitration.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Putnam, Benjamin. Boston
    Perceives that M. Gérard's absence has prevented any knowledge being obtained relative to his affair with Comte d'Arbaud. Has discovered a mistake of the Notary Public at Guadeloupe, concerning the name of the commanding officer who so rudely interfered in the affair of the prize, "Terrible"; gives the authentic names of the commanders of the frigates.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Holker, Jean. Paris
    Enclosing Mr. Williams's letter; begs that Mr. Clement be spoken to in regard to it and tbat his answer be transmitted as soon as possible as the affair is pressing.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] December 11; A.L. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Is angry with him, he captures a whole army in America, burgoynes Cornwallis, takes cannons and vessels, munitions, men, etc., and the Gazette alone announces the news to his friends, whilst he gives no sign of life. He must feel twenty years younger because of this good news which should bring a lasting peace after glorious war. Shall remain angry with him until she hears from him; in the meantime shall compose a triumphal march for him and shall send it to him, write him, and even love him with all her heart.
    Printed in Proe. of Am. Philos. Soc., XL, 107 and also in Putnam's Monthly, Oct., 1906, 39.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Grand, l'ainé
    Begs that he will write at the bottom of the enclosed summary everything he knows about Major Franks, and what he thinks that officer has done with the carriage so obligingly lent him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Vaughan, John
    Desires to settle in Philadelphia, the further home of arts and government; asks for advice and letters of recommendation. Through Mr. Carmichael, has heard the news of the capture of Cornwallis and his army; hopes it will hasten the procedings of the dilatory Spanish Court; this victory together with the latter one of General [Nathanael] Greene against the Charlestown garrison, has entirely freed the Southern Colonies from their long sufferings.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 14; A.L. 3p.; -----, -----. Nantes
    Sending two little works in verse which were published at Nantes during the celebration there of the birth of the Dauphin. Requests Franklin to present them to Mme. la Marquise de la Fayette.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 15; L.S. 2p.; Saint-Auban, Jacques-Antoine Baratier, marquis de
    Reminding Franklin of his promises to dine with them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Espivent de Marcel, Mme ----
    Is the sister of M. de la Villeboisnet; begs his influence for her son who wants to be a midshipman.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 16; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Estaing, Charles-Henri, comte d'. Paris
    Expects to dine with Franklin at Madame des Deux-Ponts's; offers him seats in his box at the "Comédie FranÇaise" for the same day.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 16; A.L.S. 4p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    Letters received from Mr. Dana, who has been politely treated by the Marquis de Vérac; when he wrote, had not yet communicated his mission to the Russian Ministry; his opinion of Dutch policy not raised by his journey to the North; great respects for the Dutch Minister at Petersburg; speaks prudently of the Prince de Potemkin, the Comte de Panin and the Comte d'Ostermann. Considers the last speech of the King of England rather inflammatory; his admiration for the art and address with which England manages Holland and some of the Northern powers; Lord Stormont's acceptance of Russia's mediation between England and Holland, a masterpiece of its matchless effrontery.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Vernier, ------ chevalier de
    Concerning le Sieur Vernié who entered the service of the United States in 1777 and has lately been reported killed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Dorlay, Eleazer. Mill Prison
    Was gunner on the Continental ship, "Confederacy" when she was captured; his present cruel confinement; begs Franklin to procure his exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 17; A.L.S. 4p.; Suavelier, -----. Caen
    Assistance he has rendered Americans escaped from English prisons. Desires the position of Consul-General for the United States in Basse Normandie; sure that M. St. John de Crevecoeur would endorse this appointment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 18; A.L.S. 4p.; Seckendorff, ----, baronesse de
    Her son a lieutenant in the regiment of Anhault; desires to serve in the American Army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning his appointment as Deputy-Consul of his district which Mr. Barclay is willing to authorize; reasons why he would like it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Stourm, Jean-Louis
    His fortune not adequate to support a family of five children; if the United States will provide him with a comfortable position, will devote himself to their service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Thayer, John. Paris
    Account of Franklin's perfect benevolence not one whit exaggerated; has experienced it himself; expresses the most enthusiastic gratitude.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Franks, David
    Enclosing a letter from Mr. Jay, which advises his return to Spain, and his departure from that country to America; desires Franklin's opinion; is persuaded Mr. Jay has something of consequence to send to the Congress and wishes a trustworthy messenger. Complains of his treatment by the commandant; believes M. and Madame Deseitre, persons of infamous character, are at the bottom of it; the lady has imposed upon Mr. Hancock of Boston and consequently on several respectable people in Brest.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 20; L'Accademia di Scienze, Lettre, ed Arti, di Padova. Padus
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Bouvinghausen, Maj. Gen. ----- de
    Sending a second letter for General de Steuben, which he begs Franklin to guard until the Baron's arrival in Paris, if the report he true that he arrives in January.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Bondfield, John
    Enclosing the form of passport granted by Franklin and desiring him to make any alterations which he may judge proper in virtue of recent changes; inclination shown by their merchants to unite in commercial interest with the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Angus, John. L'Orient
    His return after being captured in the brig "Franklin"; has not taken command of the brig "Antonia"; this vessel being American property, begs for a commission and letter of marque.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Pope, Jacob (prisoners)
    Begging their exchange; in all about sixty or seventy prisoners, who were captured in the West Indies, and sent to England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Willcocks, Robert. Havre-de-Grace
    Requesting that he and his lieutenant be set at liberty, or at least informed of the nature of their crime.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 21; A.L.S. 4p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Has acquinted Mr. [Samuel?] Vaughan with directions concerning Mr. [Henry] Laurens's support. Succeeded in removing Mr. Gouverneur to better quarters. Need of a further remittance by the beginning of January; nearly eight hundred prisoners in all; question of procuring a speedy exchange. Comparison of the circumstances of Lord Cornwallis and Gen. Burgoyne; the Ministers' predilection for the former.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Edes, Caroline. Versailles
    Did not receive Franklin's favor of the 10th inst. until too late to wait upon him. Encloses Mr. Bridgen's letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Brissot de Warville, Jacques-Pierre. Paris
    Project on a work on legislation.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, IX, 114).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] December 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Clémemderin, -----
    Sending him a memoir concerning an affair of consequence to every French corsair.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Franks, David
    Denies that the lack of consideration shown him was due to any indiscretion on his part; before this time, has always been treated by the French with the greatest politness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Varenne, ----Desouches de
    Desires to know whether he can rely upon facts stated in the "Brief Account of the American-English Revolution from 1774 to 1778" by an American; needs only Franklin's endorsement to continue the work he has projected; mentions the principal statements the veracity of which he desires to ascertain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Benyowsky, Maurice-Auguste, Comte de
    Sending the first part of his memoirs, and the journal of his voyage to Kamchatka; promises to forward the rest of his memoirs and his journal of Madagascar.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Barclay, Thomas. Amsterdam
    The owners of the two vessels, who have the clothing belonging to the United States, have agreed to deliver it upon the conditions enumerated.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 24; L.S. 2p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Terms and conditions made with the owners of the ships who have agreed to deliver the goods to Mr. Adams; they will pay the owners and Franklin can reimburse them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] December 25; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Enjoys Franklin's pleasantries in what he calls his bad French. Thinks much better of his French than he does himself. Wants him to write often.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, October, 1906, 41.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Louis Sazérac l’ aîné & fils
    According to orders received from Mr. Bondfield, sent Franklin a turkey stuffed with truffles.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Clegg, Edmund
    Introducing Mr. Henry Wild, a prudent man who has a scheme to lay before Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 26; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Searle, James. Paris
    Reminding Franklin of his promise to send him an introductory line to the Marquis de Castries.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 27; A.L.S. 1p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Confirming their former statement that the Continental goods are now at the disposal of the Hon. Tho[ma]s Barclay and His Excellency, Mr. Adams.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Webb, Benjamin. Pent
    Pays his respects to Franklin. Has been with his eldest boy in Switzerland; his wife an invalid; is visiting Mr. [Robert] Pigott.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Vinfrais, -----. Villejuif
    Asking for leave of absence for Jean Pierre Le Duc at present in the service of South Carolina, who received two wounds as mentioned in the enclosed certificates.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    Introducing Mr. William Cheever, of Boston, who expects to spend some time in France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Richard, Jean François. Paris
    Apology for not informing Franklin earlier of the loss of the "Alexander," a prize made by the "Indian" now called "South Carolina"; owing to his wounds and lack of money, was obliged to rest some time at Dunkirk. Hopes to wait on Franklin shortly and ask his kindness on behalf of certain American Prisoners, whose names he mentions as having fought with singular courage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 28; Mem. 3p.; Feray, Jean Baptiste A. Havre
    Applies to the Untited States Congress and to Dr. Franklin to be appointed Consul for the United States at Havre.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Hoffmeister, H. Adolphe. Heidelberg
    Franklin's kindness to his brother-in-law and to himself.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Epidorge, ----. Dunkerque
    Begging his influence on behalf of Captain Conyngham's crew who, since 1777, have awaited not only their wages but part of their prizemoney.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Account of money paid to Col. William Richardson and sundry prisoners arrived from England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Berard, Simon. Paris
    Sending the enclosed from Capt. John Angus and endorsing his request for a commission.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 31; Chaumont, Marie-Thérèse Jougues Le Ray de
    Wishing him a happy New Year and many of them; congratulates him on the surrender of Cornwallis. Her affection and admiration for Franklin and her friendship for his grandson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781; A.L.S. 2p.; St Esprit, Abbesse Marie du
    Sending him all good wishes and acknowledging his past kindness with gratitude.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 31; A.L. 1p.; -----, -----. Madrid
    Mr. J. has called to see him; said he was disappointed at not hearing from Franklin, as he expected both advice and financial help from him. Mr. J. seems to be in need of money, he still owes the writer 30,000 piastres.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781. December.]; L.S. 3p.; Brillon, M. et al
    A serio-comic address to Dr. Franklin from Nice by the Brillon family and few mutual friends on the occasion of the New Year.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, December, 1906, 316.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.]; A.L.S. 1p.; Alexander, Alexander John. Paris
    Returns papers taken by mistake from Dr. Franklin's office.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780 ?]; L.S. 2p.; Bart, Jean
    Formerly of the Continental brig "Lexington"; petitions for wages and prize money due him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781]; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Breton, ------. Paris
    Enclosing a letter from M. Peuch, proprietor of the Utrecht Gazette, and offering to forward Franklin's reply.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1781 Friday; A.L. in 3d P. 2p.; Brillon, M
    Sends a letter which he has just received from M. Didelot "Fermier-Général" recommending M. Gellée who was about to depart for America.
  - to Benjamin Frankllin, [1780 After Aug. 16]; A.L. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Requesting letters of introduction for M. Dillion des Gayères who was leaving for America to take charge of food supplies for the troops.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1781; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Cannot take breakfast with him. Is still weak and much affected by the disaster which has happened to the Bouffé house. The ladies of that house were her friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780 After July 10]; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Has been very seriously ill. Will not be able to go to see Franklin for a long time.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1781 Thursday; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Premises to dine with Franklin. Thanks him and his son for their kind attention when she was ill.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] Monday; A.L.S. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Invites Franklin to spend a few days with her and her mother at their country place.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1781; A.L. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Believes in being punctual and faithful with friends even in small matters. Is leading a quiet, uniform life in the country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [(1778 ?) ( Nov.) 11]; A.L.S. 2p.; Brillon Mme. La Thuillerie
    Last letter she will write to Franklin from this place. Returns to Passy next Monday. Is often dissatisfied with her own letters; do not fully express her sentiments. Will continue, however, to write them to Franklin who should soon have a volume of them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] 13th; A.L. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Will return to Passy on the 21st. Hopes to see Franklin every Wednesday and Saturday evening at tea with her usual guests, Le Veillard, Abbé de la Roche and Abbé Morellet, Mme. Grand and her niece, M. Grand and M. Pagin.
    Printed in Proc. Am. Philos. soc, XI, 105 and in Putnam's Monthly, Oct., 1906, 38.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779? Feb 24]; A.L.S. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Has been very ill with a nervous trouble. Did not receive visitors, but sorry they did not make an exception in his case. Asks him to call to see her as soon as possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781. June?] 13; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Complains of Franklin's forgetfulness of her. Has learned that he was at the opera on the day the building was burned down. How uncertain is life and by what a slender thread it hangs. Without the sweets of friendship, life would not be worth living.
    (In French)
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Nov., 1906, 170.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780 Dec. 7]; A.L. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Has been ill for 69 days. Asks Franklin to write to her if he cannot call to see her. Hopes Franklin will find her letters easier to read than formerly, as she now writes in a larger hand on his son's advice. If she were a journalist Franklin's works in French would soon be published. Is afraid her husband may steal some of the droll stories which she is collecting for Franklin's amusement and tell them himself.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] Wednesday morning; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme. L'Arbalestre
    Referring to a day spent by Franklin with them at the above place. Does not like the idea of making a long journey the coming winter for the benefit of her health.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] Saturday morning; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Sends Franklin the music he has asked for. The idea of his approaching departure from France seems like a painful dream to her.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] Monday; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Feels it almost as hard to go to Paris and leave Franklin as to go to Nice. Will go to see him sometimes and hopes he will be able to come to see her.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781]; A.L.S. 4p.; Decambray, ------. Paris
    Applying for the position of Secretary to Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. 1p.; Chalut and Arnous, Abbés
    Returning the "Gazette of Amsterdam" and request him to send them the letter of recommendation for M. Louis Jolly.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    Begging Franklin to write at once to the Count de Vergennes, requesting an escort for the vessel, the "Marquis de la Fayette."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.]; A. Mem. 2p.; de Chaumont, M Le Ray
    Account of "interventions" in [Jonathan] Williams [Jr.]'s drafts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780 Dec. 11]; Mem. 2p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    Claim for freight due to his vessel the "Marquis de la Fayette" chartered by Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    Advises Franklin to postpone his ball to another time because of the bad news about the French and Spanish fleets.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    Requests him to notify Mr. Andrew Patton to go on board a vessel at Rouen bound for Cadiz and to give him a commission from Congress to engage in privateering against the English.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1781; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Chinon, Comtesse de
    Inviting Franklin to the ball to be given in her honor by M. and Mme. la Maréchale de Richelien.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Circa. 1781.]; N.S. 1p.; Deshautesrayes, Prof
    Inquires if Dr. Franklin has remitted to Favier the price of the 11 volumes of the History of China.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780 ?]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Dillon, Comtesse. Versailles
    Sending him a packet for America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Circa 1781.]; N. in 3d P. 1p.; The "Gazeteer."
    Sends Franklin copy of a letter which was written by a great King's Minister.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780]; A.L.S. 1p.; Golowkin, Comtesse de
    Thanks him for restoring her to life and hope. Is not yet strong enough to go to see him. Will be the first trip she will take.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [after 1781? March 7]; A.L.S. 1p.; Golowkin, Comtesse de
    Thanks him for his letter and news contained therein. Hopes to see him at dinner on Wednesday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1781; A.L.S. 1p.; Golowkin, Comtesse de
    Requests him to loan her his carriage for a day as her own is broken.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780]; A.L.S. 1p.; Golowkin, Comtesse de
    Asks him for news about Chevalier de Chastellux, her intimate friend, who was reported in the "Courier de l'Europe" to have been killed in an engagement.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780]; A.L.S. 1p.; Golowkin, Comtesse de
    Wishes to have a few minutes' conversation with him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781?; A.L.S. 1p.; Golowkin, Comtesse de
    Is again anxious and uneasy after hearing about a battle between Rochambeau's troops and those under General Clinton. Asks for a true account of the affair.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781 February 2]; A.L. 1p.; Golowkin, Comtesse de
    Asking him to loan her a French-English dictionary.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781?; A.L. 2p.; Golowkin, Comtesse de
    Baron de Blome has just called at her house and told her the good news brought by Mr. [John] Laurens about the surrender of CornWallis. Asks Franklin to lend her, for a few minutes, the map showing how Cornwallis was surrounded.